I hear you I totally get it
it's really difficult to try to balance
being up to date but also not wanting to
just fall for whatever fad or trend
happens to pop up online how do you know
who's right how do you figure out who to
trust on the Internet it's incredibly
frustrating and you're not gonna be
perfect you're gonna miss sometimes my
goal here though is to help you get a
little bit better at that science is a
great place to start right but we know
it's flawed and limited and honestly it
only represents a portion of what people
use as evidence when they're making
their real life decisions so don't worry
I'm not here to teach you how to read
research studies or didn't how to
interpret forest plots or whatever
awfulness that was but you can't just
ditch science either because it's
complicated and then turn on blindly
follow whatever guru coach or influence
or you happen to follow on Instagram
that's a terrible strategy so what I
thought I'd do today is show you some of
the tricks people use to sound very
convincing when they're actually full of
hmm more importantly what I really want
to get to is my personal approach to how
I go through some of these things and to
keep my BS detector as sharp as possible
and in case you're wondering yes I am
recording this during the quarantine
Korona thing so this whole thing you
don't worry about that you just you just
don't you worry about that so if that
all sounds exciting I invite you to join
me for the next 55 minutes or so and
I'll teach you a little bit more about
this bulletproof BS detector that I've
developed to help you understand how to
navigate this complicated arena we're
all living in right now first thing we
have to do is identify what I call your
philosophy and this could be your
personal one and you should develop this
but also the philosophy of the person
you're listening to or trying to learn
from once you understand where they lie
on this continuum then you're a lot less
likely to be tripped right because they
could be genuinely trying to trick you
or they could not you just don't
understand where they are in terms of
how they value evidence and so I showed
this video in the five-minute clip but I
want to talk a lot more
I'll talk a lot more in depth about it
now and if you didn't see the five at
one well here you go
so on the red side of the spectrum here
is what I call the gurus and I don't
really mean that with the negative
connotation I probably should have
chosen a different word because they're
not necessarily bad people or wrong
right they just tend to be people who
are the early adopters so they don't
have they don't require a ton of
scientific evidence to do things and the
benefit of that is they're way faster
they tend to be innovative so they
develop and they find things out that
scientists would never do they ignore
them without this stuff we would be in
big big big trouble the downsides though
they have an incredibly high error rate
in fact they're almost always wrong
because they're trying to do something
new they're trying to be innovative
they're intentionally going against the
green for the most part they're often
very attention-seeking they want to be
important they want to look like gurus
and experts and they want to be a
cutting edge I mean think about this
this is what drives half of social media
almost all the media right now you don't
want the person who's gonna compose a
call for this one but just about every
damn podcast I've ever been on and I've
been on several hundred now they asked
like well what's the new exciting thing
and I'm always like nothing man that's
not how science works if you want to get
the new exciting thing get on filling
the name they're like you you pick your
person who's a hacker or the block or
the person like they're gonna tell you
what's innovative I'm gonna tell you
well this took us three or four years to
figure this little thing out and it
helped us learn a little better but
that's because I'm a scientist I am
clearly more towards the blue end of the
spectrum what you'll see a little bit
later and that's not better it's not
worse I actually fundamentally think we
need people on both sides it's very very
helpful I know there are planning things
I have learned from the red end of the
spectrum and a lot of times things that
start in the red end up being in the
blue so that's fine it's I'm not
knocking anyone you just have to be
careful and you have to use your own
brain to think about am i listening to
one of these people whose red they don't
really care about being wrong
necessarily in fact they're often wrong
and I don't apologize they want to just
do the next thing the next thing the
next thing and they don't ever come back
and be like oh that thing that was super
into last year and it turns out I don't
buy any more or I don't believe in it
they just do next next next next next
next next so you need in your mind go
mmm okay
you know grain of salt here they tend to
want to have a lot of attention they
tend to like to be popular and want to
be viewed of as that oh he's so
innovative or she's so advanced mm-hmm
maybe maybe not
all right you can have a higher rate
what's that saying about being on the
end of a blade or being cutting-edge all
the time you're gonna get cut a lot
right so if you don't care about that be
cutting-edge just make sure that you're
being honest with your audience
especially if you're the person names
back in the camera right the other in
the spectrum is a scientist and that's
not a fair and that's a negative
connotation as well right they're not
bad people that aren't wrong and they're
not just literally the polar opposite
but they tend to be wrong also we have
ample examples of science being wrong
and sometimes because the folks in the
red push so hard that the scientists had
acquiesced right but they're wrong a lot
less often because they're not because
they're smarter but just because they're
more conservative and if we think about
this this is probably exactly what we
want our world health organization our
national guidelines we don't want them
to be changing every month every six
weeks every thing right because if
number one it'd be really really
ridiculous to follow and it'd be
impossible to execute so we want them to
be a lot slower we want them to be more
conservative downside they tend to be
very stubborn and they tend to be very
protective of their prestige so they
don't want you know they spent 15 years
in college and six years as a postdoc
and they finally after five years of
research in their own lab develop some
pedigree and they don't want someone who
doesn't have a degree spent six weeks
trying to put coffee in their nose and
all of a sudden that person gets all the
likes on Instagram and gets all the
interviews and so that's understandable
but it's also a negative thing right
they can hold on to that position and do
anything they can to show that their
belief or their approaches is not wrong
and so there can be issues there now me
personally like I said I'm probably
somewhere in the neighborhood in tension
not an early adopter to almost anything
I don't like it philosophically for what
I do personally in my practice as a
scientist educator and working with the
athletes I like to do both there's
plenty of times that I've like I said
use things from the red and and move me
there so I'm not fully blue I
I personally believe most of us should
be more in this purple end right have
some blue folks have some red folks but
most of us a little bit purple if you
want to be closer towards the middle or
closer toward the redder end of the
purple that's fine up to you I don't
care again I'm really asking that you
think about this as your own personal
exercise and then really think about
this from the people you're learning
from and this will tell you a lot about
how they're approaching the evidence
then you know make it so much easier for
you to understand when you're seeing BS
or not right in addition just be clear
with your audience or your in the
spectrum right now once you do that then
you can implement this BS detector of it
that I've developed for you and so we
can take a look about look at that right
now effectively what you're trying to do
is figure out uncertainty so major
mistake folks makes is they want to know
what's right or wrong and that's very
very rarely the case in fact it only
happens at the very ends of the spectrum
what you really want to do is figure out
how certain versus uncertain
or uncertain is this AG specific topic
so if something is so certain that you
would say it's as certain as one plus
one equals two to me that goes on the
green end of the spectrum right and
there are honestly fairly few things in
our field that are that certain if
something is so uncertain like the earth
is flat you probably go to the other in
a spectrum right but honestly these
things aren't that hard to tell no one
has problems with that figuring out okay
the earth is not flat or yeah one plus
one equals two it's the stuff in the
yellow that's CSU and so that's why I
really developed this system or at least
I'll put it into a video for you a very
lengthy video let's help you figure out
okay well what's how do I figure out
what's a you know a five out of a
hundred versus a 95 out of 100 and what
I mean by that is this ten point system
I've created and so I tend to view all
the evidence and I'm using on quotations
and I put into ten categories each
category gets a score of one to ten
based on the strength of the evidence so
10 times 10 gives you 100 so if
something scores a 95 out of 100 it's
very close to green I would probably
call it it's not I can't guarantee you
it's right but it's as close as really
humans could ever get to
right so that's hotter % true the flat
earth would be the exact opposite right
I'll give it maybe to it 100 so it's not
a zero but it's about as close to zero
as you get I'm not interested in
evidence for either one to be honest
if something's 95 out of 100 I don't
even look at any more evidence it would
take extraordinary evidence to come in
that for me to move it into the I don't
do this anymore thing right and so
really I don't pay attention to things
that are like 90 percent or higher and I
don't pay attention to ten things that
are ten percent lower because the
likelihood of you just wasting your time
is so incredibly high yeah you might
miss one or two things but really that
the chances of something going from a
three out of a hundred to a 90 out of
100 are so unbelievably small you would
waste your whole life doing that maybe
that happens once or twice so my
applause because you saw my philosophy
right I'm more towards a blue I'm more
conservative I tend to go alright y'all
play with that stuff and if something
changes let me know but for the most
part you're gonna waste your lives and a
ton of time chasing stuff that really is
true and I'll wait till something lands
closer that 40 to 50 and then I'll watch
it if that surfs movement 50 60 then
I'll want to probably start paying
attention to it or you can start doing
it I hope that hopefully the system is
making sense now right so we take that 1
out of 10 and we make these mental
spider plots now I don't literally do
this I don't have a spreadsheet and I
don't have scores and this is well
mental right and I'm trying to take note
okay
all right looks like the evidence is
maybe the 510 and now watching it 20 30
okay watch it from I'm watching from the
side oh wait from 2032 five kids out you
get the idea here right you can imagine
scenarios and I'm just watching to see
how things progress typically now we'll
get into the more the details later but
every single thing will have necessarily
score 100 0 to 100 that means higher
scores better so there are plenty of
examples that I will show you where 20
out of 100 is all I need to be 100%
confident in it I don't need any more
evidence there I'm gonna go ahead and
take action there are plenty of times
when something is an 80 out of 100 I
still don't do it right I want that
confidence level to be higher and so you
really have to think about the question
and think of
your philosophy where are you out of the
spectrum how high do you need to see
this needle move before you start to
take action or you believe in something
all right and so all I really ask is not
that you don't do things that are can
out of a hundred I don't really give a
what you do do everything that's
zero matter go to your deathbed thinking
the earth is flat I don't really don't
care all I ask is that the strength of
your conviction conviction equals the
strength of the evidence so if you're
like hey man I totally believe the earth
is flat oh really where's your own ow
damn it there is no evidence but I just
really I feel it I don't care
it's when you misrepresent the science
or the the depth or the quality of the
science that people get really mad so if
you're proposing something then it has a
score of twenty out of a hundred and it
should really have 80 or higher before
you take action but you state that hey
look there's not good evidence here but
I'm doing it for these reasons totally
fine all right just make sure it roughly
matches the strength of the evidence
where people tricked you and this is
kind of what I'm getting at is the
following three ways number one they
could just make things up I don't really
want to talk about that here though
that's not the confusing part people can
just make up things in life and
hopefully we eventually figured out
where people tricked you is number two
and three so number one they are number
two they don't divulge their place in
the spectrum like we just talked about
right there's a difference between the
evidence and your opinion and it both
are appropriate I'm thinking of coaches
things like that where their opinion
their expertise is more important than
the quote unquote evidence all right and
so again no promise either one just make
sure you're breathing very clear or not
misleading which goes into number three
which is a conviction doesn't match the
strength the evidence and this is either
because of or phosphors dell'utri and
ideologues and so this is the classic
example of wow it worked for me
therefore it must be true for all of
humanity
oh there's no evidence or there's
evidence that shows the contrary but I
don't care it's my identity we have huge
problems with this in the nutrition
space and I'll show you some some things
that stand out and that later but you
know like if your name on your social
media profile is the nutritional value
like I find it very hard to believe that
you're gonna listen to any new
in evidence it's a year 91 it's too
ingrained in your personal self to make
a change it's generally not a good thing
all right so we want to be really
careful especially when the strength of
the evidence is minimal all right that
we aren't all of a sudden because it
worked for me because I like it because
it fits my personal philosophy in the
world or life or other things or my
religion that therefore I'm a hundred
percent convinced it's true despite the
evidence being 30 out of 100 right so we
just can't have that mismatch along the
case what we tend to see here when
people write books or do that the worst
thing ever
documentaries podcasts etc is they
misrepresent the well-roundedness of the
evidence and or they cherry pick and so
they'll maybe go into one of the ten
categories and just hammer you the
evidence there and don't reveal the fact
that oh yeah all the evidence in all the
other nine categories shows this as a
terrible idea and so you're like wow I
guess there is a lot of evidence there
but there really isn't there's just a
bunch of evidence it's a classic example
of imagine if I did this all right you
like Wow three out of three this is
perfect but I'm like actually there's
six things here I just didn't show you
these three and all three of these
actually say these are all real in fact
it gets even worse because there's
actually a hundred behind you're not
saying I'm just showing you the three
represented ones right so that's not
really showing the fair breadth of the
evidence and this is why people like me
will classically say things like this
ready ready for this cliche term you've
heard you have to look at the entire
evidence base you can't just pick what
the experts are saying you can't just
pick the pre and post pictures if
there's no other evidence to go from
fine take whatever they have but when
there's other evidence you have to
represent all of it and that is gonna
give the viewer the most well-rounded
understanding of what the information
really looks like and that's what we're
after right so a couple of notes before
we jump into this more specifically all
ten of these major categories these
types of evidence I'm gonna be talking
about right I'll go through each one
individually and give examples all ten
have major limitations the weaknesses I
am NOT the science guy is saying all the
meta-analysis is the best
are that know every aspect of science
every type of study every type of
evidence you could ever get has huge
limitations weaknesses you can't get
around them there are biases that are
subconscious that are completely
intentional and they're charlatans that
exist in all ten so there are scientists
that make up science they're scientists
that don't make it up but they have an
unintentional bias there are coaches
practitioners a Salesman and supplement
industry folks I just make clothes cause
the whole board right and so that's
always in it but I don't want to talk
about it more today because it doesn't
really help what we're trying to get out
all right all of them can be faked the
reason in fact I'm gonna present to you
this lengthy system if the system's
actually pretty short but this lengthy
discussion is because when you have
multiple types of evidence that you use
you're less likely to be tricked if all
you pay attention to our systematic
reviews if a scientist came along and
faked one of those then you're screwed
if all you pay attention to is bloggers
and hackers and people with big
followings and people that have been on
in popular podcasts but well when we
expose those folks as being liars as
well which many of them are then you're
screwed you're looking even you feel
like you got fooled again
and so when you take all of it into
consideration though you're less likely
because those red herrings will stand
out right those sore thumbs you're like
wow the intervention studies the chronic
studies the acute studies all say oh
this thing doesn't work but yet you're
over here on Instagram ad Hocking it
like it does great hmm
something isn't lining up there and then
you can investigate further or wait for
more evidence I don't know who's right
or wrong but you probably should go hmm
I used to really think this thing works
but it looks like all the studies are
showing it doesn't I must I'll use it
but I'm just gonna back down my
confidence quite a bit it's actually
really hard to judge scientific quality
so this is why I'm not teaching you how
to read research methodologies and
cetera without extensive training I see
people do this online all the time and
it always makes me shake my head unless
you have a lot of training probably a
PhD level or higher
you probably shouldn't try to judge
science quality because you really don't
know what you're doing
I again I see this all the time
and it's kind of laughable so honestly
for the most part mmm don't spend a lot
of time here
number three pointer not all ten are
warranted or possible you have to think
about the question I've alluded to this
already in the previous disk or so far
as I've gone along but the classic
example is this right so you don't need
a meta analysis you don't need a
systematic review you don't need
molecular research on how are the
mechanisms to understand that you should
not jump out of an airplane without a
parachute so in fact if I use the system
I'm about to show you the whole idea of
jumping out of a plane without a
parachute would probably only get about
a 20 out of a hundred in terms of
evidence but you don't need it you don't
need to understand none of that stuff is
needed and so not like I said not all 10
levels of evidence are warranted or
possible there's a lot of things and
decisions you're gonna have to make and
your life and your coaching line where
you can say hey there is no research on
this and that's fine that doesn't mean
it's it's bad or it's against the
evidence base there is no evidence base
to use and so I would really really
really encourage you to think about the
question does the question need
intervention science yes it does
okay is the intervention science no
there isn't okay then I'll go to
something else maybe writing it may be
able to do the molecular stuff it's not
as good but that's the best I have or
does the question need theological sense
yes it does okay the teleology
says it this thing doesn't work hmm okay
does you get the idea
it could be a whole spectrum of things
no it doesn't need these things so I
don't care what the mechanisms are so
not all 10 categories are possible or
even necessary all 10 should not be
given sick equal or even wait.you again
you have to think about the question
that tack thing so that depending on the
question the molecular data maybe ton of
it but it may not be important at all
you may really care about or what all
the experts are saying all right we're
the people that actually use it how does
that actually matter and we see that
happen Kozlov we see misrepresentation
or over exaggeration or over
exaggeration sorry overhyping of
molecular or acute data when we get to
the chronic or long-term and it doesn't
matter at all right so not all
necessarily have equal weight so an 8
out of 10 in one category may not be as
important as a de to 10 in another
category you have to think about the
question
so exactly example could be this so
let's say you were trying to look at
some medical question Ryan you wanted to
know what surgery method is the best or
you know what to give somebody or how an
ER doctor should operate in this
particular case you care about the
meta-analyses right you probably care
about one of the molecular mechanisms of
this drug or this treatment etc one of
the other doctors that I've been using
it were they saying what a clinical
trial is looking like but you don't give
a about your intuition you don't
have any intuition about what drug to
take for your infection you don't have
any clue you don't care if it's natural
or not any basically every medical
procedure is non natural so well is that
something that we evolved who cares no
we're definitely not so that's not a
knock against what you're doing it's not
relevant to the question right and
depending on what you're going after
teal illogical may make sense chronic
may or may not make sense so you may
come out and say these things don't make
sense when it comes to like a lifestyle
question it tends to be pretty opposite
so in this particular case you may or
may not care about like the results of
the meta-analysis because a lot of our
lifestyle stuff there are no
meta-analysis so it doesn't matter right
there's nothing to draw fall but in this
case you will care a lot about the
anecdote you will care a lot about TV
ology on the nature right in fact nature
has a very very very high watermark for
me when it comes to lifestyle things
because if we did were naturally meant
to do it I don't really care if there's
molecular evidence it's you know
teleology is probably more important
naturally more important here I don't
care if there's a acute response if
we're not seeing it long-term etc right
if you know all that made sense
maybe the examples we got you later well
but hopefully that helps you understand
again there's not equal weight and Yuri
category think about the question and
which type of evidence would be
necessary and needed for it so a couple
last little notes here before we
actually start going through some
examples again this example I could give
you the exercise is good for your health
problem
like a 93 out of my nerd score so I'm
not thinking about it I don't care if a
new study comes out and shows oh it
didn't improve lipid paths I don't care
a lot of information I have to come out
to really reduce that score to a level I
start to question why not exercise is
good for y'all because it makes sense on
basically every level of evidence
alright and finally being wrong is
totally ok
I can't I've been wrong plenty of times
I will continue to be wrong just don't
misrepresent your evidence so now what I
want to do is I want to go through these
ten categories of evidence one by one so
you can learn a little bit more about
them because that the titles are a
little bit deceiving and then I
deceiving they just there's more to them
than that all right so our first
category is what I call them analysis
now I don't literally just mean men
analysis this could be anything like a
systematic review position stand so
major organizations like the NSC a is SN
World Health Organization etc they tend
to come out with every year six months
five years whatever position sans where
they say hey all of the scientists on
our team generally feel this the issn is
particularly good at this so is an assay
by the way fantastic of going through
all the research and area and then
saying okay this is what we collectively
think is pretty important and so all of
the things in the meta-analysis category
what they generally mean or they take
huge chunks of information huge amounts
of authors now hundreds of studies
together or dozen studies thousands tens
of thousands hundreds of thousands of
people involved and they put them
together and they summarize the research
and so they have a pretty good power
there now I don't necessarily think
these have to be peer-reviewed research
it could be giant databases so if a
company or like all the the data on
strength training from Russia you know
they had thousands ten hundreds of
thousands of repetitions logged over
decades of training they're not these
are on all equal levels of evidence but
to me they're all important right so it
doesn't have to just be peer-reviewed
and I throw these all in like
meta-analyses categories so in general
the strengths of these is they are
typically viewed as kind of like the
strongest highest
of science because the data points are
so numerous and you really get a feel
for what's actually happening and they
are fantastic for large population best
practices prescriptions so if you want
to know how what's the optimal
repetition range for hypertrophy we're
gonna throw all these studies together
and say hey look in German what we're
typically finding is this so best
practice says stay within this range or
whatever the case might be eat this much
protein or whatever else is important
for a supplement and so some fantastic
examples of proper interpretations of
these things I talked about the rep
range one some of the initial research
on figuring out smoking was bad the
meta-analysis started coming out we're
like jeez it's really bad alright the
science got really strong there you know
decades ago
you can thank every Fagan bomb for this
stuff but we wanted to know that it's
strength training actually bad for kids
and the meta analyses are incredibly
clear that it's not in fact it's
generally very very good and positive
for children people often claimed about
obesity makes you fat it's our fruit
makes you fat etc and the meta analyses
in this show very clearly fruit doesn't
make people obese in fact it generally
helps a reduced body body weight and
improved body composition whole fruit
consumption whole fresh fruit
consumption so this thing's like that
these were all different things that
people use they used appropriate or
predations meta analyses and and they
have pretty high certainty levels
because of that the downside of these
categories they completely eliminate
context or nuance right so they are the
antithesis of individual coaching you
can't just take somebody and all of a
sudden say okay because a meta-analysis
said this therefore all kids should lift
as heavy as possible not at all what it
says we're just saying as a best
practice in general strength training is
safe for kids does that mean every
single kid whose strength trains is
going to find no and so meta analysis
does the exact opposite of allow
individual and precision coaching
because they say okay take all these
studies studies that were done on old
people and young people and healthy ones
and not let's throw them all together
and see what generally happens so by
definition you're eliminating context
and
the ability to judge the science the
quality of it like I said you probably
need to be a scientist to get through
that so don't worry about that too much
but another downside is if you've got
crap data in you're gonna get crap data
out so I do see a lot of meta analyses
and position stance and stuff where
you're like wow there was not enough
evidence for you to do meta analysis how
did this get through peer review but it
does so low-quality studies into a meta
analysis is gonna have a little quality
meta analysis and the biggest con is
incredibly slow you're probably looking
at at least a decade for a meta analysis
to come out on a topic if not two or
three so very slow right however good
sources to find them pubmed is fantastic
Google Scholar can get them if you're
ever been on Google Scholar or PubMed
and you found an article let's find a
paywall you can also try the third
option I have there which is a research
gate a lot of times are up there I'm
free there are several companies now at
least in the Sports Science Committee
that are that are doing these scientific
reviews so these are you know two to
five people with PhDs or something like
that and they go through the science and
they come up with they're kind of all in
meta-analysis published but they usually
have these on low price subscription
models five ten fifteen bucks a month
things like that and they kind of review
the science for you and those are really
helpful in generally high quality or you
can go to websites like exam comm if you
want to look up nutrition information so
good places to get them there the next
category are what I call chronic now
these are not the same if you're
scientists you like goddess in our
chronic studies I know know what I'm
talking about here but in this category
these tend to be for me a long-term
chronic stuff so this could be things
like epidemiology it could be like five
or in the case of like a study I did on
lifelong exercisers about a decade ago
technically the the groups were
comparing had 50 to 60 years of exercise
history we did one on twins a couple of
years ago and at 35 plus years a
difference I'm not talking about like an
eight-week strength training study I'm
talking like huge databases of stuff
again it could be a database from a
private company or a coaching platform
or you know something like that you're
gonna find these and pretty much
the same spots that you're gonna find
the meta-analyses because generally tend
to be sciency things they're strong
signs not typically viewed as high of
science as a meta-analysis but the nice
part about these art is they they show
the clinical important effect so what I
mean by this and we'll see this when we
get to the molecular stuff later is the
end markers for epidemiology in these
long studies tend to be things like who
lived longer or who got stronger who had
less pain and so the outcome measures
you're looking for are what we call gain
clinically important so you're gonna
feel a difference you're gonna notice a
difference this is actually something
that a real human would care about and
that's really really important because
not all science can do that and I'm also
great for what we call canary finders so
epidemiology gets a bad rap but like any
piece of evidence their strengths
weaknesses right how epidemiology
specifically is supposed to work is
they're supposed to find Canaries and so
good examples of this or things like HPV
so the we found figured out the cure for
HPV because of Epidemiology lots of
kidney disease and renal failure said
been found the same thing it's like we
do epidemiology we see Wow all these
people in this population have this
issue then we dive deeper that is how a
PD me ology is supposed to work it is
not if the answer itself because the
negative the downside of it is it only
shows you correlation it rarely rarely
can show you causation so because of
that this chronic type of evidence tends
to show you tons of what we call
spurious correlations if you've not
familiar that term Google that there's a
website it's hilarious it just shows you
all kinds of funny spurious correlations
right and so the example of HPV we
started seeing correlations between X
and and people who are getting HPV then
you started looking and doing further
research to intervention research things
lower levels and start to realize yes
this was causing that so the benefit is
we can look a huge databases and find
major trends we can find these Canaries
in a coal mine downside is it doesn't
show us cause almost ever vo2max
mortality was another one right
this is when we started to notice Wow we
put 80,000 70,000 people in these
database and we start to figure out the
people at the higher vo2max is live
longer
the ones with lower ones die sooner okay
it's pretty important that we look into
this further
is this something we can train well if
so how do we do it and does that improve
lives so it can be really really
important
we need you've heard the downsides of
this type of research right and also
because it's big database stuff it
eliminates context and nuance you have
to a lot of times rely on things like
recall hey what over the last 30 years
what have you been eating and you know
that's probably pretty low quality
evidence so it depends on the study
specifically this is saying it's
incredibly slow takes 50 years to build
these databases you know theoretically I
mean they just they do this retro
actively but you get the idea but the
other big thing that people have pay
attention to is really conflates risk
versus hazard all right you need to
Google that and then look into that but
it it's not the same thing and it can
really really confuse people so we see
these numbers torn out all the time this
reduces mortality by thirty five percent
okay did it reduce your risk of
mortality by thirty five percent or your
instances of mortality that's very very
different right if your risk was 1% and
it took you from 1% to 1.5 percent
that's a 50 percent improvement but I
could say hey this improved lifespan by
you know our reduced risk by 50% mmm
okay not really
it took me from one to one and a half
percent that's not clinically
significant I don't really care about
that right so you have to look at
there's more than that but you have to
look up risk versus hazard two very
different things
okay the next step down or the next
category bad example forgot that classic
bad examples of Epidemiology were the
fact that they assumed the single factor
cause or causality and this is a classic
example of Oh meats bad for you nope no
it's not it fails and I really level
which we'll go through
or if you stopped here right so if you
just take AP ml and you say hey there's
this correlation therefore this thing is
causing a bad factor which is again
exactly what people did when they tried
to claim meats bad for you
it's just bad science you're taking one
level of evidence ignoring all the other
levels of the evidence and giving a bad
outcome so you assume the single factor
because typically to me epidemiology
puts a human's life hey what have you
been doing the last 30 years and they
tease out one factor oh it's because
your hair was blue what it didn't have
any do with my exercise my this and why
that or that or that
and that's not really what affects
people's health for example is one
factor so it's hard for them that
account for reusable we call covariance
for multiple factors so they tend to do
one or two or none and then you get bad
bad signs from there my next category is
what I call interventions so these could
be things like as short as two week you
know training studies or up to even like
five year long
it could be randomized control trials or
clinical trials could be practitioner
data right so hey I've been coaching
these Division one athletes for five
years we collect their vertical jump
every day and that's not peer reviewed
it's nothing exactly these are not the
exact same things but to me that's
that's pretty important information as
well so the strength of these
intervention studies are they still are
you know science they have methods and
things like that they can be anyways and
they do start to give you some
indications of cause and effect hey we
did this this group got this this group
got this plus that and here's the
different results so we assumed we're
pretty sure that it's because of this
change so it does give you some
indication of cause and effect and
because of that unlike the first two
categories these interventions can give
you specific recommendations
alright this group got three milligrams
this group got ten milligrams this group
got a hundred milligrams a three
milligram group did better therefore we
recommend you take three milligrams
that's pretty damn helpful epidemiology
can't really do that in systematic
reviews depending on what they are they
can or can't do that
so these things can titrate stuff out
classic example here was creatine
so when we started doing these
intervention studies in the 90s we
started saying when you take creatine
for five weeks
well you get a lot stronger than if you
did the exact same workout ate the same
thing slept the same way and didn't take
great team pretty good evidence that now
creatine works this is why it's you know
I'm very far end of the spectrum in
terms of strength of evidence that it
does a lot downside of interventions if
you've googled around to this you
realize there's a massive
reproducibility issue with these types
of studies there's a massive problem
with what we call internal versus
external validity as well as things like
or this would include things like okay
it was done in a bunch of untrained
people is that gonna be the same thing
in my Olympic level sprinters okay yeah
maybe maybe not probably not I don't
know and so we have other issues that
all there's a bunch of stuff that falls
under this reproducibility issue you
controlled something things in the lab
therefore will actually count in the
field or you didn't control for anything
so how do you know this effect actually
matter that's internal versus external
validity they also tend to be short term
so we see these problems like okay yeah
there's no difference between the groups
after eight weeks but what if you would
have continued the three years now we
would have started to see a difference
well it's hard to do an actual like
intervention study for more than a few
years without a tremendous amount of
funding and you especially can't do that
in athletic or sports science because
they're not out of the sport they're
graduated they're gone
athletes don't do that so these it gets
pretty tough in sports science to do
anything longer than a few weeks and of
course because you're trying to do a two
to two week date week to five year it's
very very slow not as slow as the
meta-analyses but slow so a classy
example of a misinterpretation here
we're to use intervention studies for
things like this right so imagine you
did a study or looked at a study on look
that compared eight weeks of linear
periodization versus nonlinear
polarization did it and I'm trained
people okay that's helpful but that's
probably not gonna tell you a lot
because generally peers Asian is
something we're looking at over the
course of six eight months a year and
you didn't untrain people and so the
first four to maybe even ten weeks the
adaptations are probably gonna be pretty
similar because
their training level is so low and so
that's not necessarily not saying those
are bad studies are about science but
you couldn't use that so therefore
there's no difference between these
types of training well there may be but
maybe not in this population and maybe
not in this domain so that would be
maybe something you'd have to have you
couldn't take that previous information
say okay look we're a hundred out of a
hundred here we know linear is better
than nonlinear or whatever
okay this helps us adds to it but mm-hmm
you know we're not too certain you so
good examples of places to get
information from intervention stuff the
ones we've listed before but this is
also a place where you can go to clinics
and conferences webinars and social
media a lot of people put information
out like this that's very easy to get to
so I would strongly encourage if you're
in this area of sports science to head
to ISSN or NFSA maybe ACSM but not
really or or a similar event and go to
these national conferences or local
clinics or regional ones and you can
learn a lot of information about this
level of science which can be very
helpful for you continuing to work our
way down now we get into what I call the
acute studies so this could be anything
from like a a single second so I give it
to them and I immediately measured their
blood or whatever up there maybe like a
couple of weeks this could now also
start to include things like animal
research so we did this study in rats or
we did it in cell culture it could be
things like practitioners hey we did
this the person then all sudden that
this is what happened all important
pieces of information that it still can
be signed so that's another con now we
really really start to get
cause-and-effect right so like hey we
put this on their hip they went to the
platform this is what happened that
didn't happen couple even literally did
it immediately and so this is pretty
clear evidence that this is causing that
effect whatever that effect was and the
accused stuff tends to be very good at
describing what happened then tell you
how or why I'll get to that but it does
tell you what happened you did this and
this is what happened you took this
thing this is what happened and because
of that it can provide you pretty
specific recommendations classic
examples are hey you took caffeine all
of a sudden your aerobic endurance
improved you took it right now you went
ran a mile you ran that my
faster than when you did yesterday when
you didn't take the caffeine pretty good
cause and effect and we're pretty good
confidence that it actually works
same thing for muscle activation right
so we looked at when you put your feet
open and you did your hip thrust and
then we looked at when you put your feet
close and you did hip thrusts and when
you did it this way your muscles are
activated differently or whatever right
can be very very acute when you stand
this way you do this when you stand that
way you did that those are appropriate
uses of acute type of information the
downside we still have reproducibility
issues mate major problems with EQ stuff
internal extra mobility is a problem but
the biggest issue with these things are
the correlations between acute response
and chronic adaptation those can be
really bad so for example just because
you took caffeine and ran faster right
now eight weeks later will you actually
have better endurance when you go to
race in your competition we assume that
a lot and a lot of the times it is true
but it's not necessarily true and I'll
show you some examples in just a second
fact let's do them right now so the
classic example of protein synthesis so
if you take a biopsy out of a muscle and
you want to look at the rate of muscle
growth same thing with a signaling
aspect of it here so the molecular stuff
is very clearly just because one thing
has a higher rate of protein synthesis
another one so you compared this
supplement to this supplement a2b just
because one has a higher rate of protein
synthesis we eight weeks later you might
have the exact same amount of total
muscle growth so they're not unrelated
but they are not it's not linear so the
acute response doesn't necessarily
guarantee you the chronic outcome and
this is really rampant in the protein
synthesis research or the this and the
muscle signaling stuff the gene
expression so if you have a 5x increase
in the gene that makes you grow more
muscle you will not have a 5x increase
in muscle growth ten weeks later not
even close
and so the cube responses do not predict
the actual long-term outcome for a lot
of things other examples this are like a
fasted versus a fed
study so if you did hey study where one
day participants came in and fed on a
bunch of carbohydrates and then we ran
them on the treadmill the next day they
came in fast and we ran them on the
treadmill
hey they ran better when they were full
of food there for training with full of
food is better for you well that's not
necessarily true because you're ignoring
the fact that well sure they're hungry
today but actually after three or four
or five or six weeks or something they
would adapt that so once they're adapted
now they actually still run slower maybe
maybe not you don't necessarily know
because you're not or you're taking a
shock to the system you're comparing
that assuming that they won't ever adapt
that and we know people do adapt really
really really well we saw this with and
this was a an appropriate criticism from
the keto diet folks when it was like hey
we gave you a whole bunch of fat no
carbs one day and you're not used to
that and then we have you do endurance
exercise well of course you feel
terrible because you're not used to
using the fattest fuel once your body
learns how to do that you get better at
it and that was partially true they
still suck than just a lot of things
there but those criticisms aren't
accurate to this type of acute stuff so
same same they happen with what the one
I'm calling like inflammation folks so
people look mmm
the acute studies a lot when it comes to
things like oh this food cause more
inflammation therefore it's worse for
you that's not true at all right not
even close because just says some that
causes more information again it may
cause a manic response and you may
actually reduce your information because
of that your inflammation and so the
acute response can be used in fact these
this is the type of research that
honestly probably is the easiest to
manipulate in terms of taking advantage
of people um it can be you don't know
the difference or you're trying to do it
but you can use this stuff to make a lot
of points and we have to understand
acute versus chronic right and some good
places for this as standard science
places but this is where I'll caution
you for the conference's clinics
webinars and stuff you really have to
understand what you're talking to you
because like I just showed you it's very
easy to manipulate the acute science
stuff and this brings me to our next
level which is the mechanism stuff
so these are like zero to 48-hour
studies animal cell stuff these two
things like you know we looked at the
blood or we looked at the cell or the
genes or anything where you looked at
the mechanism of how a cell adapted
right so this is the real internal bio
chemistry biology type of stuff
pros very good science and course they
give you specific recommendations and
now with this cause and effect thing we
started to explain to you how it's
working and why it's working so not just
saying when you took this drug you
jumped higher it's saying you took this
drug and jumped higher because this gene
got turned on and this is what happened
with adrenaline and your muscle got
activated higher because this was
released more etc so it tells you the
mechanism of how things work and so
proper ugh some examples of some proper
interpretation here this is how we
learned that this molecule called mTOR
is related to muscle hypertrophy great
therefore if you turn this thing on or
if this thing gets turned on somehow
you're gonna induce some muscle
hypertrophy that's fantastic and very
helpful to understand this is how we
figured out maybe stem cells or
potential helpful for injury recovery we
start injecting stem cells once we
learned what they are and how they work
molecularly
we started saying man if I put this in
somebody's shoulder its inflamed
maybe they come back from injury and
voila it started working sometimes
antibody development you wouldn't be
able to take any kind of pharmaceutical
drug without having the molecular
mechanism for this stuff out right so
very appropriate uses of this types of
research their downsides still have
reproducibility problems it's extremely
short term and you think the acute stuff
was bad this is even worse and we tend
to get really exaggerated effects so I
mentioned this a second ago but this one
is one of my biggest pet peeves and
there are people who live and die on the
mechanism stuff and they sound really
smart right so they'll go on a podcast
in Alaska hey what do you think about
fish oil and they can give you a 20
minute explanation of wow that it
activates this molecule which activates
this one it causes that it causes a 40%
reduction there and it's almost all
exaggerated right as I just mentioned a
50% improvement in or reduction in
inflammation
might not have any clinic clinically
meaningful result right and so it
doesn't scale like that perfectly so you
have to be very careful take advantage
and manipulate things like percentages
all right so you have to understand well
if I increased c-reactive protein by 13%
does that matter it turns out at us
getting more like 13,000 percent
improvement to actually see anything
happen there you don't know that you
have no clue right and so these people
tend to get very excited about the
micronutrient stuff or the molecular
piece of it when they're taking that
stuff very highly out of context and
they're exaggerating the effect again it
could be intentional or could not be
right we have to marry this stuff and
match it with the actual outcome the
intervention stuff so because of that
the validity tends to be questionable
and we have a problem of no what we call
reductionism and so we bring it all the
way down to the most microscopic level
we're actually losing the big point it's
even Google reductionism if you want to
learn more about that human is another
major issue so here's a couple of very
specific examples I just told you a
second ago how one of the major benefits
of this mechanism stuff is we learned
that mTOR is related to muscle growth
but the major downside was in therefore
assuming more mTOR means more growth and
we know that's not true at all so that's
a very poor thing so we can't for
example do the study and say this
workout caused a greater release event
or therefore it would cause more growth
okay well let's do the a week train
study and see who grew more well it
turns out they both grow the same so
that's not an employee isn't related
it's just that it's not linear like that
it doesn't work the same way so that's a
really inappropriate use of this type of
research basically anything lighted the
aging umbrella this is what they do
right they take studies from earthworms
or at best rodent models and say hey we
um we fasted them or reduce their
calories by 13% they lived 40% longer
okay sure
what happened when you did it with
humans no yeah though they lived eight
days longer on average great so all of
aging research for the most part is
based on this molecular stuff and a huge
percentage of these either extremely
exaggerated or not clinically relevant
so it wouldn't actually make a
functional difference in humans
we have species compatibility issues so
fasting is another classic example of
this when you looked at it in the sum of
the cell culture stuff on earthworms it
looked amazing and fine
in fruit flies but when we was
reproduced in humans it showed it didn't
do anything and so we know for example
metabolism does not scale linearly so
things like fasting tend to have huge
impacts and small animals but don't do
anything in fact have negative impacts
in the bigger animals so we have to be
very very careful whenever we're using
mechanism and again let me look clarify
this doesn't mean those types of studies
and cell work is not important in fact
it's very very very good look at the
blue stuff that's all coming from cell
culture stuff initially and then animal
models and a lot of stuff we learn comes
from those things we have to have that
stuff it's very important everything has
a strength and a weakness right every
level here so good sources here is going
to be a classic science stuff for the
most part right and so you can see all
those things we've been there before
okay now we're gonna start Xing Atta
they're kind of like sciency stuff and
get more towards the other end of
spectrum and the next one here is
teleological and so you can google what
that really means but the short version
is this things like they would fall into
this umbrella to me not necessarily all
things to steel illogical but just
things like oh did we evolve for that
why would it do that what's the end goal
does this make sense that biology would
actually set it up this way and so the
nice part about it is it tends to win
the long game what I mean by that is
ideas that pop up you're like okay it
looks like some science is strong here
but this doesn't make any sense
teleologically give it a few years and
the science will probably correct and be
like actually this doesn't work at all
fasting is a great one right it's also
very helpful when science is not
available or limited right it's kind of
like your gun is now why would it do
that does that make sense that would
happen there there's no science yet so
it actually makes that sounds like it
makes sense I was like this is why a
cell would do that okay maybe legit
there and it does correct overzealous
science like I just mentioned right so
it'll help you kind of bring things back
to maybe over exaggerating or just
exaggerating sorry the molecular stuff
for the acute
if it doesn't make sense that way good
examples are things like rotating
feeding patterns it probably does make
good tea low in logical sense that we
don't eat the exact same meals and have
the exact same eating style and have the
exact same amount of meals our whole
lives we probably would have never done
that as a species and so it's probably
good for us to rotate the types of food
we have and the style we eat and maybe
do some fasting maybe don't do maybe
we'll move things around a bit that
probably makes them theological sense
things like temperature and sunlight we
probably did get cold at some point we
probably did get hot we probably were
exposed to the Sun so these are probably
things even though the science isn't
there yet this makes some intuitive
sense we should look and it's doing some
science here because hey probably
important for the cell to get that
exposure chronobiology is a kind of a
new area of saying oh well what about
maybe making sure we're go to bed when
the Sun Goes Down and waking up but it
comes up and kind of matching our
biology to the sunlight and things like
that or the time of the day that stuff
makes to you lots of sense so science is
very limited in all those areas or at
least it was a few years ago and now
it's really starting to come out but it
kind of made sense from the beginning
the Khans science is highly flawed right
so it's not particularly great there and
it's mostly speculative and so you can
really justify and logic yourself into
anything here all right this is a
classic well if you think about it and
you can enter a whole bunch of logic
anything like this and the science here
ok and if you're good at making
arguments you can make anything sound
appropriate it gives too much credit to
evolution so at personify cells
personifies chemistry really well it
would never it you know mTOR once I'm
sure doesn't want to do anything I'm
course not a human it doesn't have a
brain that I'm a consciousness so tell
me logically there's problems if you
want to get Google around teleological
biology and there are some major issues
with it but doesn't mean it's completely
useless either so a couple of examples
of on the negative side here are things
like carbs are toxic so for a handful of
years we had to hear about how
carbohydrates are what caused all your
dimension and aging why there doesn't
make any sense why would
behind reeds be bad for your brain oh
yeah it turns out you're completely full
of
that's nothing no okay yeah are there
problems with overconsumption sure but
would do we would make anything a
logical sense for a carbohydrate to be
bad for human to consume we saw the same
thing when we're like okay great
humans didn't evolve to sit all day
therefore sitting is bad okay that makes
sense
I came following here but where they
went wrong without it was there for you
stand all day like wait why we weren't
of all the staff of it either probably
standing is if we're gonna compare them
probably better than sitting but humans
evolved to probably move and so general
movement is probably the thing we want
to go after not just sitting or standing
cuz neither one of them really involves
movement so things like that right we're
mistakes with teleological good places
here this is anthropology helps us a ton
right and going back to one of the
negative things is the problem with
anthropology is it changes a lot and
it's very limited I mean think about it
we're trying to make interpretations
what he was did 30,000 years ago how
much evidence do we really have and it's
probably based on you know like one or
two sites this is your classic examples
here like Oh humans never did this
thirty thousand years ago they never ate
this what really pretty sure like how
could have a sample size do we have of
all humans thirty thousand years ago or
five thousand years ago for that matter
and the ones in the Amazon did the same
thing as the ones in the Arctic and the
ones that not that doesn't know so
anthropology is very very limited in
sample size there right your brain like
that's the best source of this and then
some books but I put this in yellow
because you got to be careful your um
most authors will try to trick you with
T biology and then put some references
in there and it sounds like a science
but it's really not all right and then
coming down the end here is what we call
natural and so this could be thinking
things like there's similar to geology
but could be like wow this is natural
with what it would we have done this
when we have been evolved to do things
like this very hopeful in science is
limited and like I said it as correct
the overzealous science and so things
that are good here these are actually
all ones that I created so I remember
actually
probably being 12 and running in my
giant thick-soled shoes and being like I
don't think this makes me run right I
don't feel very comfortable in this and
I saw I remember as a teenager being
like man we shouldn't have these people
thick soles on our shoes we probably
wouldn't have evolved to run like that
it's changing how my feet are running so
I didn't really need a lot of science
about at that age to be like hmm because
this is not natural this is probably not
optimal and turns out we were right
about that right screen time right I
have two young kids right now in a
toddler we probably would have not spent
15 hours a day staring at a screen eight
inches from our face so probably smart
to have been like hmm maybe we shouldn't
do that we shouldn't do that with our
kids at age one probably correct their
human connection is another one
hey we probably evolved to be around
people so it's generally probably maybe
not a great thing for our mental health
to be very isolated living through
social media another favorite example
actually put this in the book my book
unplugged sanitizer right so when we
first developed hand sanitizer was like
fantastic sanitize everything and then
it was like wait a minute here we
probably didn't evolve to be completely
free of all bacteria oh yeah it turns
out we started learning about skin
bacteria and how important that is and
maybe we shouldn't be that's actually
funny I'm doing this part during the
corona but right you got some point
maybe we shouldn't have evolved or we
should kill off all the bacteria in our
mouths on our hands all around us
because we would have never done that
before we evolved to live with some
bacteria all right so the cones are
again it gives too much credit to
evolution evolution is the thing it
necessarily doesn't have a it doesn't
necessarily have a consciousness it
enables nonsense justifications and it
has the natural fallacy so you can look
in the natural fallacy but just because
something is natural doesn't mean it is
actually right or good and that's the
major problem with this level along that
line is natural also doesn't mean
optimal so this is because it's how you
would naturally do it doesn't mean it's
optimal example they're being teep oh we
never evolved to brush our teeth sure
but what else died at 30 when our teeth
fell out so natural can you know has
limitations like anything else and a lot
of other downsides here is it tends to
disregard
science and so can people uses that we
would naturally never done that I don't
care what the science says and that's a
bad take awesome
so some classic misses on this one were
things like bananas oh you shouldn't
need a banana bro why cuz naturally
before he was got involved they were way
smaller so who gives a
what's that mean nothing like they used
to be ten grams of carbs in a banana now
there's twenty okay so now you eat half
the amount that you used to you probably
would eat 50 of them before and I eat
two
who cares that didn't make any sense at
all the science doesn't support that in
any direction video games right well we
used to think oh man kids would have
never played a video game so it's really
bad for their health even to read a book
and now actually the literature says
actually problem-solving follow through
then there's nothing wrong with yo games
maybe actually some of them are good for
your brain development you know hey if
the herbs are better than Big Pharma why
if it comes from this planet earth
that's natural
so just because the product you're
having is all natural versus
pharmacological doesn't make it any
better for you were healthier for you
even close
certainly it probably makes it less
effective some of them are more
effective but it could be less effective
but then the assumption is it's more
natural it comes from natural plants
like the pharmacology stuff didn't come
natural plants at some point also
alright so some good sources there again
anthropology your brains just thinking
through things some books and the
hippies this is where that edited of
spectrum helps us see how and again we
mocked them and laughed at them for
decades and this one it's like well
after you'll probably pretty ride this
all right moving along then we come to
anecdote and this could be from a
scientist could be from a practitioner
we could look back and maybe the history
see what people have done before or one
of my favorites that the classic N
equals one in other words your own
personal experience what have you tried
your self experiment my friend Brian
Mackenzie is doing awesome stuff right
now on his platform well depending on
when you see this it could be five years
from now I don't know but he's doing all
these N equals one experiments he's
helping people run their own self
experiments through his stuff so I check
that stuff out he's doing but you know
the benefits of anecdote right it's very
clinically relevant but by definition
almost and it's also very scalable
which is really really cool and
individualized and scalable in terms of
you can all try you could do it a bunch
of different times it's really really
really fast you can do as many of these
as you want there's no limitation enough
to wait for funding all this stuff so
it's super awesome that way my favorite
example is there you know like I said
this is this is basically what my entire
book unplugged is all about is how to do
your own self experiment and how to
balance the science and the technology
with what your body is actually telling
you to figure out what's right for you
not necessarily what's in the
meta-analysis the downside of anecdote
though why we don't why we actually have
science right it is placebo right if you
don't control a lot of things and
because you know you're putting yourself
through something almost always your
mind is very strong and good at tricking
yes you don't really actually know if it
worked or not it has an extraordinarily
high error rate because of that and we
have problems with the the true for me
so it's probably true for all so I did
this experiment and I lost more weight
this way therefore the whole world
should do this that's not how anecdote
works all you can say is this is why it
worked for me it worked for me great
hope it does for you too and we also
have things like spontaneous remission
so a classic example of instead of
taking my cancer drug treatment I ate
only juiced celery and then my cancer
Amelia went away well yeah maybe the
juice celery oh we also have these
things in biology called spontaneous
remission where things go away and
change and you don't know why and so you
don't necessarily know it's because of
that thing you tried from your herbal
health store or something and so we've
missed this a lot common mistakes with
the anecdote are thinking that the
plural of anecdote equals data is always
saying so in other words just because
you saw website and they have 50
pre-post pictures it's as good a sign
it's not because they probably 5,000 pre
post pictures that sucked
not telling you or whatever right or
they're not controlling for a lot of
things this is also exactly what leads
to fads and trends for the most part
people I tried this and worked right oh
my god Emma was trying is trying it yeah
well we can explain that extra
scientifically and we know that happens
and then six weeks later they're all
back to where they started or worse or
the next thing pops up right anecdote
effect
the other than aversion is a scientist
right where this is like well if it's
not a comes from an RCT it's wrong we
shouldn't do it and then that's the
wrong approach to we should promote
people knew their own self experiments
start with science science is the
foundation but you've got a self
experiment from there and we shouldn't
discourage that just because we don't
have a randomized clinical trial to give
us the direction to go so good places to
start there some books can be really
helpful
social media clinics talking to people
working with experts hiring a coach is
probably my strongest recommendation and
then doing your own and equals one
experiment so that being said we'll go
to our our second and last category I
think which is our expert so these are
people or organisations with extensive
what I call high quality experience and
the upside of this is they typically or
they by definition they have extreme
depth of knowledge and experience this
can't be replicated in any other
previous levels it's fast and extremely
precise prescriptions it's exactly what
you need and why because it's gonna look
at a lot of categories they've seen this
thing a whole bunch of times they have a
ton of experience doing with it my
classic examples are things like Mike
Boyle right Mike Boyle is we'll just say
a very polarizing figure in the
strengthening community
he hates basically sports science but he
made some innovations in the field
because he did it a lot he practiced
with works with a lot of people and he
made some really important innovations
in our field without doing a single
thing in football for pretty much hating
science the whole time but he was an
expert he figured some things out and
that helped breathwork
I'd say would be another one so there
was Hindus and shamans and things like
that that we're doing this breadth work
for a long time and they were you know
it's been years meditating for example
or had trained a hundred thousand people
in spark and seen things and we can
learn actually a lot from them and have
I mean it's like breath which is classic
example something with no science behind
it a few years ago now the science has
really caught up about these experts
really know what they're doing because
they'd spent a lot of time in doing him
Jimmy Radcliffe another example
legendary speed coach strength
conditioning coach from the University
of Oregon I don't care
a single one of his methods has ever
been supported a research study he's one
of the most legendary documented coaches
ever I'm making people fast and strong
specifically strong I'm sorry
specifically fast and powerful and
jumping so he's an expert he's done this
he did it I think for 25 years organ or
something like that I will trust his
depth of knowledge and experience in
those realms downside how the hell do
you know who's qualifying to pay an
expert I don't know really really tough
right staying in your lane so I would
listen to anything Jimmy Radcliffe ever
had to say about speed training but I
don't care I don't give a crap about
what he says about nutrition right don't
care at all and we see this a ton with
things like TV doctors like bro you have
a PhD why are you telling him giving us
a medical advice you're completely out
of your lane right TV and DS are the
worst about this like your your
cardiovascular surgeon why are you
telling me anything about nutrition
you're completely out of your lane
you're using your expertise falsely it
doesn't cross things like that the
classic logical fallacy here's what we
call the appeal to Authority or
tradition all right so Jimmy Radcliffe
did it therefore might be good that
doesn't mean anything or Michael Jordan
did it so you should do it this way that
doesn't mean anything that's a logical
fallacy right other examples and there
were early stages of the ketogenic diet
or Paleo diet for that matter it was you
know people talk about it like it's a
panacea it's like Oh keto is great why I
it's better for fat loss it'll cure your
cancer it does blah blah blah I know
that was true right it wasn't as
bad as some of us thought but it didn't
do any of the things people were talking
about for the most part even the experts
were going on there claiming it did it
but I did right but scientists did the
same thing right well when those people
that loved Taketa were telling us fat
isn't bad for you and we were like no
it's bad for you and the experts and the
nutrition experts were saying fat is bad
fat is bad and then we had to realize oh
it's not so both sides have made
mistakes here right and so you have to
be careful with experts they're not
perfect functional training was another
common one right where you see
Instagram coaches and stuff now and
doing all this crazy functional training
stuff and you're like wow he trains this
person and look what he does that
doesn't matter it could still be a
terrible method right and a lot of that
stuff was really kooky
strength training stuff hi Tatiana hey
you want to be on camera come here
err want to say hi to everybody yeah no
you know what I say had anybody ah
they're trying to learn about science
and be smarter yeah yeah I would you
rather have lunch than be on camera you
want to sit dad's chair okay well you
got to go see mom for a few more minutes
okay sorry about that
yeah so our sources good places to learn
from experts conferences clinics books
podcasts social media all that stuff
just like everything pros and cons here
and then last one is what I call your
spider sense or your spidey sense and
yes i spelt it wrong intentionally but
this is your intuition right unconscious
knowledge is very real so we should pay
attention to your gut right just because
you can't justify logically why
something is sounding good or bad to you
that doesn't mean we throw it out
entirely it's individualized right it's
your sense and it's fast and actionable
again I can tell you several examples
not the sound like try to convince you
have some RNA everything but just these
are personal examples for me calorie
counting right when it came to people
saying no calories don't count my spidey
sense for like what that's the stupidest
thing I've ever heard
and then science comes out yeah of
course calories count dummy like that
didn't make any spidey sense to me at
all
heel squats I remember being taught to
squat on my heels and I immediately and
ever since have been like this doesn't
make any sense to me
it doesn't sound feel right pedal I
don't think I should squat fully with
all my weight on my heels I should use
my whole damn foot toe Sprint's so I
remember also the first time I put on
track shoes and I sprinted and I was
like wow people telling me to run on my
toes but that doesn't sound right either
I should probably run on this middle
part
hello static stretching same thing right
all these things that didn't they never
made any spidey sense to me my intuition
was just like no I don't think of you
stretching my hamstring for 30 seconds
right before I go run 100-yard dash
I don't feel fast anymore don't feel
springy I feel like I've lose some of my
pop so those didn't make spidey sense to
me the downside of using your intuition
is myself included is we're all very
stupid and convincing nice toe there's
not a lot of your own thoughts going on
your head almost everything is coming
from the outside marketing is very very
real you can be tricked and convinced
into having your own intuition and
typically also because we have any
complete information so other things
that have been silly um you know again
breathing training I talked about the
second ago but that didn't make any
sense to me at all my intuition was like
this is all dumb and I was definitely
wrong about that steady state training I
used to hate steady straight endurance
exercise didn't ever made sense to me at
all now I realize that was a big hole I
should have worked on that more machines
I used to hate exercise machines like
the bench press machine dumbbell machine
or squat machines on them oh those are
stupid those no way intuition was wrong
and they're very very useful now that
I've got a little bit older right so the
good sources of your spy since are you
dummy you're right
your intuition right so now we've
covered all the categories a little bit
of overarching information here about
where to get information from so this is
my list of basically worse places you
could get ever get things from
documentaries TAS atop that list
I don't watch documentaries about
anything sports science related and I
haven't for decades
I haven't probably the mid-90s they're
terrible they're awful they're the worst
place ever to get information from books
can be the same equally bad but one
thing I won't recommend is a website
called red pen reviews it's really cool
to go to to figure out kind of the
quality of accuracy of books so you can
start there if you're interested in a
book check it out a red pen reviews and
then you can come back and decide to
read the book or not but especially be
wary of books from people that have
companies or influencers do you know
they have a vested interest in what
they're selling their entire idea is to
try to get you know I love when they
actually
they come a scientist they're like well
hey that science is invalid because it
was funded that science that showed
choco milk was good is invalid because
it was funded by chocolate milk
yeah author who's selling a book your
whole thing is to try to generate
attention to get more things to your
book you are equally of conflict of
interest so just be very careful of
people who again have a specific company
so if they run a keto company of course
they're gonna put out information that
shows pro keto if they are whatever like
you get the idea it doesn't mean it's
wrong you just have to be really really
have a major conflict of interest
similar thing for people whose
livelihoods or identities or research
agendas so it could be science as well
are specifically tied to one approach so
we see this a lot of scientists so
they're trying to prove this thing and
of course all the information they put
out is gonna be Pro that they're trying
to protect their careers and protect
their funding and it goes both ways so
if anyone's social media handle is Quito
Dave or you know conjugate system you
get the idea right if it's in their
social media house and their profiles if
it in their BIOS they are admitting to
you that they are incredibly biased and
are it's so tied their identity they're
probably not going to listen and change
of the evidence so it'll be very careful
getting information from as we call
those ideologues right books by MDS
Piske throw them out unless it's in
their specific MD training
so again if you're a cardiologist I
don't really care that you read a book
on strength training it's not your
expertise your MD doesn't matter not
that mean you're wrong but your MD has
no relevance at all to what you're
trying to sell me on news of any kind
just gone leave it don't watch it don't
read it it's all out for me at this
point and the final piece here is people
who don't utilize information and their
expertise at all so what I mean by this
are okay you're a hacker and you're
trying to give me the next supplement
for cognitive improvement do you use it
every day
oh no you used it three days and then
wrote this blog great out
oh you're scientists and you want to
promote the benefits of training like
this do you train like that
no do you work with people like that do
you actually coach people no you don't
okay I'm not saying all this means are
irrelevant but this is we have to be
very very careful if they don't use it
themselves when they don't work with
people who use it yeah mm-hmm again not
singing out not always possible here but
work gosh so now what I want to actually
do is start going through a bunch of
examples so here's what I've done I've
shown you one of these spider plots or
these radar plots and around the outside
of my circle are our ten category sign
meta-analyses chronic interventions
acute etcetera cetera so things are in
the very very middle of the circle means
they have a zero of 10 score no Elevens
things are on the old on the outside of
10 so ideally we want things as far on
the outside as possible so when I go
through is three different concepts and
I'm just using this to show you how the
radar plot will work I'll go through
specific examples in a second say you
had concept number one it looked like
this so I had strong meta-analyses data
eight at a 10 there your intuition was
really good you think it really works
poor scores for chronic evidence
intervention stuff didn't work but the
acute response looked great the
mechanism looks great maybe make some
theological sense but you don't really
know anybody who's using it not a lot
anecdote to it experts aren't loving it
how would you interpret this obviously
is not a 95 out of 100 it's not a 5 out
of honour'd either so where is it well
to me this is the classic example of
something that's probably being over
interpreted and so what they've done
they looked at the acute response maybe
oh there was maybe a molecular response
and then they had some meta analyses
come out on it we don't actually know if
it worked right because there's no
chronic studies there's no intervention
studies you don't actually know if
anybody's ever used it all those
categories that involve people using it
and seeing an outcome have low scores so
to me that's probably over interpreted
and doesn't mean I don't think it works
but I'm not gonna use it yet until I've
seen some documentation or somebody try
it and see some actual effect let's take
a look at the next one what about here
basically you seen scores and anko and
an expert and nothing else that's
probably not
with my time okay so some people tried
it and some other person who has
actually since something did it and they
liked it a lot but we've got no data
anywhere else that doesn't mean I'm
gonna not do it or say it's wrong or
false but hey you got a total score of
17 out of a hundred
you remember where I'm out of that
continuum right
I'm way down the end of the spectrum so
to me this is something where I might
loosely pay attention to but I'm
probably just gonna disregard for now
I'm not gonna go anti against it and
post about how it doesn't work but I'm
not paying attention to it really at all
and then of course the other one this is
what we're looking for here right so
concept three it's got good scores
everywhere else maybe there's no acute
data to it or something but it looks
pretty solid I'm probably gonna say it
works and honestly I'm probably not
gonna pay attention too much more to
look for the acute data maybe the acute
data it's on the make sense here maybe
it's not necessary or maybe those
studies were low-quality weren't done
right or whatever but in general hey
this looks like it's pretty effective
I'm probably gonna try and see no
guarantee might not work with me
personally but I'm probably gonna try
and see so let's go through some actual
topics and see how these things stack up
so you can learn about the topic but you
can also again learn about the system so
the result of this one is actually that
we don't need science so now that I've
told your result what do you think would
look like I'm the omnes spiderfly here
so what would what categories would be
high what categories would be low for
the result to be I don't care it didn't
need science for this maybe something
like that right so maybe something has
perfect scores basically an anecdote
natural teleology and your instincts
there's no science whatsoever on it this
might be your parachute example right
great fantastic I'm doing this a hundred
times out of 100 and I don't need a
single score in science to tell me that
if I jump out of a plane I'm gonna die
without a parachute so I didn't need
science there another example that might
not need science may look like this
so maybe doesn't make any natural sense
and I'll tell you a logical sense a
little bit of intervention to chronic
data but no acute no mechanism
and this may be something like a
coaching example so hey we know that the
conjugates system works for getting
people strong why look at what they've
done they've got 30 years of extreme
success they don't have any men analyses
and there's a little bit of like chronic
stuff and inventive stuff on some other
parts of the system but I don't care
what the biology says and it doesn't
matter that doesn't make any why we
didn't evolve to lifteth bands who cares
the anecdote and the expert and the
instincts are really high I pride on
these signs on that one
here's another one and your end result
is science can help you but you need to
accept experiment from yourself what
would that look like on your spider plot
science can help you get started here
but you need to experiment maybe
something like job right and get a lot
of anecdote experience our experiment
our experts like it maybe makes a ton
mmm it should work that way and there's
some acute intervention stuff there but
we haven't seen the chronic day to come
out yet we haven't seen the long-term
data and then maybe something like this
you wanna know which type of lifts works
your quads more your quads your personal
quads phone squats or lunges
well the science can't really tell you
that because your biology is unique to
you and so the science can give you like
best practices and maybe a coach an
expert to say no definitely I've been
doing this for 25 years personal
training people and generally hey the
front squat is a lot better for quite
activation and lunges there's no
necessarily chronic 35 year training
Studies on that nobody knows or cares or
Whoopi there's no molecular mechanism
nobody knows who cares
doesn't make any natural sense who cares
so the science can get you started
though probably you can say hey look the
research done so far on muscle
activation does show that the front
squat is typically more here ok great so
we'll start there about me personally
depending on my leverage and my lunging
style I may have a different result from
the science so the science can help you
get started but you'll need the
experiment on yourself from there
next result here science is all is all
you really need and most likely works
now I've already actually covered this
one here's your spider plot and maybe
it's something like what do I take for
an infection right yeah it doesn't need
to make natural sense I'm gonna have to
have an instinct
hopefully the experts are high on it
saying yeah we've used this a lot and it
works but I don't really need the
practical side this it's just basically
a science question what's the sign say
let's do it
okay now the inverse here now I'll start
with the spider plot and you tell me or
you think the example is right so maybe
you find some experts that are really
high on this meta-analyses chronic
intervention stuff is really low and
maybe there's a little bit of mechanism
but it makes no TV logical sense makes
no anecdotal sense it goes against your
instincts it doesn't make any natural
sense this is the spider plot for me for
the saying that meat is bad for your
health and for the expert I only put
that at 10 assuming you found an expert
who's really against meat say they're an
MD they're really against me they sound
really convincing it's not actually most
experts in the field don't agree with
that that's not a longer than false
impression but that's what it might look
like right and so this is why this
argument that meat is bad for your
health is so poor it fails so massively
you might be able to cherry pick a study
or two from one of these areas but if
you look at the whole base of evidence
it fails on almost every level you might
be able to pick up some of the
mechanistic stuff and say hey when you
consume me it does this to inflammation
or it has these carcinogens in it sure
but when we look at the acute
intervention chronic meta-analyses
doesn't making natural sense doesn't
make teleological sense we don't see
people who are eating meat and dying all
over the place it really really fails as
an argument right so I'm not saying at
all that vegan is bad or vegetarians bad
not even close but the assertion alone
that meat is bad for your health it just
fails it's a really bad argument and
it's unfair to represent it that way if
you want to make
you shouldn't eat meat for other
rationale fine you could totally do that
but for this argument yeah it doesn't
really shake so it's extremely unlikely
and basically it's close to false as we
could possibly get okay another one here
highly exaggerated animal or sell
results and unlikely to be very
important to humans it would look
something like that again I've kind of
talked about this example of
exaggerating the molecular stuff and
getting really excited about that piece
despite the fact that not showing in the
other areas and this would be
intermittent fasting for longevity right
it just doesn't shake out you can get
really excited about the molecular and
earthworm studies but every other aspect
it doesn't really fly besides maybe
natural I had probably naturally we
would go periods of eating and not okay
sure yeah I buy that but everything else
is it's not really looking like it's
shaping up to be very strong okay
another one I put this in the list
before but this is even worse right so
greatly grossly exaggerated animal cell
stuff unimportant humans and even
possibly dangerous so this is a classic
example of something that was taken
straight from the molecular mechanism
massively miss applied and in fact
actually hurt people I was metformin all
right so there was a lot of people who
were like wow let's start taking
metformin in our 40s to protect us
against aging because of over
exaggerated or just damnit exaggerated
sorry molecular stuff in fact just
misinterpreted not doctor stuff
despite no evidence anywhere else in the
platform and in spite the fact that the
logic behind it was really poor people
push the push to pushed it and he's
right aging experts and how great this
person so innovative and their forward
thing right until the clinical trial
started coming out showing this is
crippling people's muscle mass oops
yeah if you would looked at the whole
evidence base you'd been like mmm no
this is not very convincing at all I'm
not saying you should never do it but
those people should have been like look
I'm doing this there's not good evidence
for it
across the board but this is what I'm
doing and then when that stuff came out
they should have been retracting and
apologizing anyways here's an example of
something that's maybe got my attention
and I'm like I think maybe there's
something here yet but we need more
evidence and maybe you look something
like that
so my instincts are really high on it
maybe yeah people are trying there's
some good anecdote maybe I try to
unliked it and the experts are back and
forth on it makes a lot of TV logical
sense mechanisms are there and this is
stem cells right if you look at the meta
analyses and cronic and intervention
stuff right now is really 50/50 or less
but because of how it's working and the
other stuff I really think there's
something there too using stem cells for
injury but not here we're missing
something big-time we haven't figured
out how to use it or how to manipulate
it exactly but I think something is here
but they're so classic example of I
really do think science will be there
but my confidence isn't high because the
evidence isn't strong yet so I think the
future is strong for it but currently
it's kind of a guess it's like 50/50
right now may work may not and then we
have something that would be more
classically mostly wrong and you can see
this as being clearly driven by anecdote
which is not fine anecdotes fine as long
as this is supported by everything else
but this was classic paleo right paleo
because our ancestors didn't eat paleo
or didn't eat carbs until the China
science on that change or we realized
yeah yeah yeah I did also that doesn't
make natural set and there was this all
kinds of logical problems with that
gluten being bad well gluten is bad if
you don't tolerate it well but for those
that do it's just fine all right so
there was all kinds of holes in that
logic mostly wrong the very little total
evidence that's Aikido eight years ago
all right so we had a lot of anecdote
coming out it actually does make some to
a logical and natural sense that we
should maybe do some periods of being a
high-fat low-carbohydrate that's you can
make that argument there but there was
no science there's not Stata there right
but here's the cool thing about keto
look at the ketone
it turns out they actually got a lot
right I got a lot more wrong like again
kitto doesn't stop even get a cancer any
other nonsense claims but there is merit
there and so look at the the spider plot
was kind of crappy there and but Luke
gets moved there is a lot of scientific
support now meta analyses are getting
there the chronic stuff is coming along
interventions are showing good stuff the
acute stuff no but that's the opposite
what you go for for keto right the
mechanisms are coming along and it does
make some decent sense so I would say
that this is a great example of I
shouldn't have been so negative - keto
when I first came out but I have changed
my tongue because more evidence has has
come along I don't still I still don't
think it's a great diet for most
performance athletes often times bad but
I actually have changed now I think it's
reasonable for non active sedentary
people it's probably fine if it works
better for you it's some probably it's
definitely fine if it works better for
you
alright so the keto folks got a lot of
things wrong but they did have some
things right that we missed on so
hopefully you enjoyed that and you
helped I don't want to finish on a
little story and this is a story about
the dragon in my garage and I don't have
a dragon in my garage I borrowed this
from two folks I borrowed this from Carl
Sagan in his famous book demon haunted
world and Carl's dragon in the garage
goes like this he says hey look I want
you to come to my garage I want you see
my dragon my garage and you go to a
garage in you know see a dragon what the
hell where's a dragon evil oh no sorry
it's an invisible dragon you all okay to
this great well why don't we just put a
bunch of flour on the ground so it walks
around and we'll see the footprints you
go oh I forgot to mention only that also
visible that only flies it only hovers
doesn't actually touch touch a guy oh
okay no problem well I have a radar
detector why don't we just actually like
put a radar detector will seem on
infrared oh no actually it's a special
dragon who actually blocks out any heat
and shoots only cold or non temperature
based flames so there's no heat there oh
okay correct fantastic um well then why
don't we just like spray some paint on
him then I'll stick to us oh no paint
doesn't stick to his go he's got a
special coat of armor you get the idea
here right
and so when we're trying to identify
basic nonsense so when people are lying
whether there's actually a real dragon
because at some point that they are
gonna be okay
well if there's an invisible dragon who
doesn't cut off any heat doesn't touch
the ground and has skin that doesn't a
lot of pain to stick to but what's the
difference between that and actually
there being no dragon at all pretty
tough to say and so your evidence has to
be falsifiable at some point and so we
have to be very careful when people use
this tactic of what we call moving the
goalposts and or making a position
completely unfalsifiable so it has to be
there so what I want to give you is this
last little piece and this is actually
my father-in-law Dave Beck and I
actually had the pleasure of having him
on our podcast a few years ago so you
can check out the episode 2.6 if you
want but this is actually him on the
cover of New York Times so he's a middle
school science teacher and he did they
did the entire curriculum of their class
and did it based on the movie Mars which
was really badass and so they put him on
the cover of New York Times but
nonetheless he teaches this exact lesson
to his students now this is his BS
detector if you will this is my
detector
he teaches eighth graders you're adults
but nonetheless he teaches them eight
points and so when you're trying to
identify the quality of evidence you
have to look number one is it coming
from multiple sources in science this is
why it's important that we make sure
it's coming from multiple labs if you
see things like well I was really
convincing evidence on something is ten
papers on it but nine are from the same
lab and same author it doesn't mean it's
wrong but I'm more convinced when I see
ten studies from ten different labs all
showing the same thing then it's it's
very likely to be true you have to
differentiate between an expert and
authority an expert is so I'm gonna know
something an authority of something is
popular we've already been through this
a bunch of times in this video write
lots of authorities md's things like
that on TV
it doesn't mean have expertise in that
area try to get measurements so try to
quantify so make sure that something you
can do is measurable and you can
actually test and determine whether or
not the effect is is true Occam's razor
so the simplest explanation is probably
more accurate one rather than the
opposite especial
there's multiple reasons that can
explain something start with the the
more simpler one are there other
plausible explanations so why else could
be causing this rather than what the
thing the person told you is that could
be the entire thing it could not be is
it mostly true so if someone's telling
you an argument and it requires three
pieces of things to be true if two of
them are true but one's not the argument
doesn't stand so it can't be mostly true
it has to be totally true or it's not
true we've already talked about is it
generally falsifiable and then ego so
are people protecting and sticking to
their explanations because of the Bears
are they willing to change when the
evidence change so hopefully those those
eight tips I think are out for to you so
some final reminders as we wind down
it's hard to be right and you shouldn't
really expect people to be you just have
to be have the right process and be
genuine and honest with people don't
misinterpret the data or the scientific
evidence and be accountable when you're
wrong most importantly load all this
stuff just be nice so hopefully this
helped you get through some of the BS
that's out there if it did you can again
thank me I did this during Corona and so
don't mind my physical appearance I
shouldn't have anything to do with the
quality of my video you know what to do
if you appreciated this you know this
these things take me hours and hours and
hours to do especially right now I don't
have the time and it's not exactly
something you do to draw a whole bunch
of attention on social medias to make it
to our video about BS detection so if
you enjoy it you know help me share and
do all that other stuff but that's
that's the only ask I have for you if
you find Thomas valuable and you
actually apply this is something learn
something I would love to hear about so
shoot me an email make a comment or
whatever to be like hey I use this I
thought about this better and I totally
changed my position on this or affirmed
either way that's totally awesome just
let me know if not peace out one love
you
[Music]